e
e e
and 33
call to the approval of the minutes from
February uh 5th
2025 Mr chair I'd like to make a motion
to approve the meeting minutes for
February 5th
2025 a second have a motion in a
second um ready for the
question all in favor let it known by
saying I
I I I I I I I oppose I have it motion
carry three subvision and Land
Development a waiver of Land Development
minor plan 240 North Plum Street
Catherine Hershey School
uh good evening I'm Ben Morton uh
landscape architect at RGS Associates uh
representing the Katherine Hershey
schools uh for early learning uh joining
me tonight um are uh Rebecca benadam the
senior director of programming Bill
mckelvie the facilities manager and uh
Sean mcbrien the communications and
media relations manager um they'll be
available if I'm not able to answer um
all the question questions that you have
um it was last February that um we
presented this project to the Planning
Commission um and obtained conditional
approval for um the facility at 240
North Palm Street um since that time we
resolved the conditions of approval uh
recorded the plans obtained the building
permit and the project broke ground in
November one of the things that hadn't
been resolved when we were presenting
the plan to you was how to use the third
floor in what's known as building four
on the property um and since that time
with sort of the community reaction
towards wanting to have more students in
the facility um it's been determined
that replicating what's on Floors two
one and two of that building um as
classroom space on the third floor was
the the way to go and so um we're here
tonight requesting a waiver of uh minor
plant submissions so that they can move
forward with obtaining the building
permit to fit out that
floor um we're not making any changes to
the site plan but there um is an
additional parking demand um as well as
utility capacity requirements which led
to the project exceeding the thresholds
for no impact plan development so in
that case then we uh submitted a sketch
plan uh met with um Lauren as well as
the city engineer to um discuss a minor
plan submission and um kind of landed on
the idea of being able to wave Land
Development since there really wasn't
anything happening with the the plan
itself um that additional parking that I
mentioned is going to be addressed
offsite at 241 North Plum Street which
is a property that um since we were last
here CHS has purchased um we will be
going to the zoning hearing board this
coming Monday to obtain the special
except ction related to that um and then
the capacity requests that I mentioned
have um been made uh with staff so um I
think the one thing to note in terms of
sort of a condition of this um waiver is
that the city engineer requested that
CHS uh purchase and provide to the city
uh 16 of the delineators um to be used
along the bike lane uh in three
locations uh just west of North and
Street um just on the approach to the
Palm Street intersection and then
between the Palm Street intersection and
the site access for this project um and
so the intent then is that the city is
going to install them uh themselves but
CHS will be delivering those prior to
the building permit being
issued so happy to answer any questions
that you have
this is one of the sort of sort of
agenda items that gets really confusing
for me because I know that you now have
the other building across the street and
so like there's a giant web now um not
that I don't obviously I uh as I stated
previous meetings enjoy the project
um just based off what you were saying
there uh my only real
concern that comes off a cup is if the
city engineer feels as though um it's
reasonable for there to be an exchange
of uh material to upkeep safety
standards um I feel like that needs to
be more than a onetime Arrangement
personally and that might not even be an
our purview I'm just kind of stating it
for the record um I I hope that becomes
a more long-standing relationship than
just a onetime material purchase uh
because you know after this one time
Arrangement if we ever have to maintain
it those additional costs then go to the
general public uh and this
development if the impact there feels
like the safy standards need uh remarket
or more highlighted for the public that
I feel like that needs to be a
long-standing Arrangement that's all I
really have to say right now
Mr Mor you said you needed more parking
spaces and that will be next on at
241 yes we already have um some off-site
spaces um that are even a little bit
further east than the 241 which were
part of the original project and then um
beyond what was required for that are
going to be at the 241 okay site
and how many
additional parking spaces yeah um we
are there were 12 Surplus spaces already
um approved for use at the 226 North an
Street sites so we're using those and
then there are 21 spaces
uh that will be utilized at 241 North
Plum Street I forgot that I have voted
these on so there are some some photos
that been
provided and so is there one in
particular Ben one two or three that is
most helpful for you
um not necessarily the and these I
should say actually were the drawings
that were provided by uh Cindy McCormack
just showing where the delineators are
going to be installed
I'm just curious what is already at
sorry uh at 241 North Plum what is that
um it's been used as office space um I I
forgetting some of the prior tenant
names but it was uh primarily office
space a little bit of uh warehouse space
for a security company um the prior
owner was also in a portion of it that's
more Warehouse was um storing some sort
of U it's the right word uh vintage fire
trucks and that sort of thing but um
we're still in the very early planning
stages of how that property in the build
existing buildings can be reused okay so
that parking that's
there is going to be used temporarily
for this no the idea is that um I mean
there's plenty of parking now now uh for
it to be used and then with any sort of
future development of that property and
reuse of it um the appropriate amount of
parking for this what we're talking
about tonight will be
maintained and that is a a requirement
of the approval that we'll get from the
zoning hearing board is that they need
to maintain that parking and if for some
reason it wasn't available there the CHS
would need to demonstrate to the zoning
officer that was being provided
somewhere else that fit all the the
terms of the special
exception I have a question with the
third floor being built out now what
will remain in that building that will
not
be put to use will there is there still
fourth floor above that or attic space
or something so there are um two floors
above that and those were already being
um utilized for office space so that so
that be yeah so that's already um
everything will now be programmed at
this point
yeah Ben Ben do you have to revise your
planning module then for we didn't need
to um because we had previously obtained
a planning module exemption for this
site when it was um slated for
residential development and then we um
were able to confirm that
that applied for the initial project and
then subsequently for this as well so
it's just the local capacity request oh
okay yeah that's that's great I
personally have in favor of U of leading
the minor plan if there's no planning
module won't hold up your building
permit but that's just
m yeah I'm also in favor of that but I'm
just curious about when when when plant
opening do you have a kind of
timeline can one of you remind me when
we're at
intending for opening beginning in 2026
all the okay beginning of 2026 great
thank
you uh the more I think about
it aside from the ballards I actually
have concerns that even the paint itself
will also wear away um for the Bike Link
because of increased vehicle traffic in
and out daily for parking demand
um I don't want to hold up the project
in its entirety but I'm just wondering
if um Hershey would be willing to maybe
go into a more longstanding agreement
with the city to make sure that the bike
infrastructure is maintained
um yeah because this this was one of my
previous concerns about when we were
going through approval was how the
development could impact the bike Lanes
with the vehicular traffic in and out
and so um you know now with the engineer
saying that delineators would be a good
idea it kind of reinforces that opinion
for me that you know there's a level of
I'm not saying this is the end of the
bike lane world over here but there's a
level of concern for safety with the
bike lane so I'm just wondering if her
would be willing to go into a more uh
longstanding relationship to maintain
those sections of the bike lane not just
a onetime material
purchase I mean I guess
my reaction to that though is that I
mean the maintenance of line striping in
the public right of way really is the
city's responsibility and it's the
city's determination to have a bike lane
and access to this property is something
that you know is reasonable for them to
be able to have and I know at our the
prior discussion you had talked about
access occurring via tobacco Avenue but
even kind of no matter where this site
gets access there will be traffic
crossing the bike lane either at Plum
Street at shipping and
so I I don't know that that really
changes things Beyond just you know and
it's a reasonable amount of site access
yeah know I definitely was a proponent
of using tobacco Avenue but I was also
hoping and part of that argument for Cy
configurations to eliminate those uh
Crossings across the bike lane uh or at
least trying to eliminate how many quote
unquote intersections there are with
driveways by maybe getting an easement
with your uh neighbor
um but now I'm also concerned because
like because like the the the web gets
bigger here because now we're talking
about offsite accommodations for
vehicles at another location which was a
part of our previous conversation so now
we're talking about another additional
section of the of the bike structure
Network um I do understand that the
municipality is required to upkeep these
things but when I think about increased
development and the impacts it has um
one I mean this is a nonprofit entity so
this velopment is really for the good of
the community as a whole not it's it's
no one is getting funds here like this
is a a good thing um but at the same
time the the development has impacts and
it's it's really a minor call like when
I'm just trying to do some Mental Math
like I they job in public works like
paint every handful of years I could
imagine delineators may be a decade um
only if they get hit so um
yeah I because like to the point about
like if we're just going by who's
responsible for what I mean I feel like
we're now a point of the planning
process too where if if this were part
of the larger plan as a whole we could
have made a condition of approval or
something or had a larger discussion at
that time about again like more off-site
requirements the web expanding but now
we're Limited in scope in a way because
we're past that planning stage and we're
now into a waiver process so it it's a
bit complicated for me but I I'm just
trying to see if we can work things out
for the better of the long-term
sustainability of the bike network uh in
relation to the way it impacts the
individual
tax I I'm going to disagree with the
commissioner asra I don't think it's our
responsibility or our perview to require
folks to be adding be painting bike
Lanes I mean this is an underutilized
parel great Community uh benefit that
we're getting here and I don't think we
want to add additional requirements I
add there's no precedent for that yeah I
don't think we can do that I think this
is an amazing Community amenity I
completely agree with you Mr St um I
would really like to uh see this project
move forward I would love to see it
opened like in a couple weeks actually
because of what you're offering to um
those individuals who are truly needing
your support in our community um and I
would like to see our commission make
this um as easy as possible for you and
your team while abiding by all of our
guidelines
any further commission
comments public
comment Mr chair I'll make a motion to
approve the request for a waver of the
minor Land Development plan I would love
to second that motion
so we have a motion on the floor to
approve the extension to 40 North Plum
Street Catherine hery
School ready for the
question all in favor let nobody saying
I I I I I
I I
iose eyes have it motion
car thank you very much sure
B text and M Amendment for new price uh
elementary
school so this is the I give you some
additional handouts um for
this um portion of the
meeting
um I don't know if you want to take a
couple minutes I know you just you just
got the materials I don't know if you
want to take just a couple of minutes to
look through
them Unfortunately they were not ready
for the meeting packet so I apologize
for that
I feel like a teacher you could just
look up when you're done reading so that
I what she said
so the memo is there just to provide you
with some um background and some
information about kind of how we how we
got to this text amendment that should
you pass it we'll then go ahead to city
council for their
approval um the impetus for this is for
the school district and the city and the
link direct to be able to work together
to create um a holistic campus what
we're trying to do is um maintain the
the park amenities that are and even
improve them that are in Brandon Park
while also giving this neighborhood a
brand new elementary school and creating
opportunities for growth for the
lanaster rep because they will have a
larger um property and they will be able
to grow their child care facilities um
and their
programming um and because this plan
preceded our rewrite of the ordinances
as we're going to be discussing more um
that that produces the need for the text
Amendment
I'm happy to take questions and um bety
Logan is here as well for
questions the so the main point of this
is we're not just planning for Price
Elementary but we're planning for the
future and to be able to go beyond and
kind of codify something that would
allow any
future consolidation or swap or along
that line or just multiple uses to be
allowed and so yes that's where we're
going with the rewrite to create this
institutional use okay and so once we go
into the institutional use that will be
that will create these campus type
settings um and so with the rewrite
that's what we'll gain makes
sense what is
um so just help me understand here um
the like the school district L moved
into the Rex building they're swapping
correct and so the Lancaster recck is
moving to that property but they're
rebuilding the school so they're
building a completely new Price
Elementary School yes is the old you on
the plan here that circled this is only
where price was so what is the zoning of
the wck property and then I guess does
this new zoning complement I mean it
would yes and so um the other other map
might be better we determine that and
the other attachment that map I think
clarifies it a little bit
more oh this is super helpful yeah yes
thank you thank you say thank you
bety very
helpful so I just have a couple
questions so if if I understand you
correctly does only one does not
currently have an Institutional use
correct okay and would once get around
to the full zoning right would
institutionally use replace yes this
okay so we're really kind of looking at
a semi temporary yes at least for this
specific property yes okay thank you um
it helps a lot and the only question I
have looking through the specific
standards uh regarding
um building coverage that we're really
we're proposing here to go from 20 to to
potentially up to 50 as Allowed by
special exception is that tied to the
specific uses we're talking about or is
it
just cter
launch if you apply for special accept
you be able to cover up to 50% of the
law for for this I don't I don't I'm I'm
sorry I'm not sure I understand the
question oh
um maybe I'm not reading this correctly
but it's saying under section three in
the PO District beyond the existing 20%
Max Max building coverage and 35% Total
Lock coverage by right maximum lock
coverage of up to 50% is allowed by
special exception so maybe mean is that
currently in the zoning ordinance
or former zoning official here U
nitpicking the
zone so that's that's where the change
is and so it's currently
20% and the amendment would make it 50%
so so my my question is is that just
is that special exception tied to any
specific use like if someone wants oh I
see what you're
School whether it's a school or
something elsewh to go there yeah I
guess my my sort of concern is that if
anyone could apply
to um push the lot coverage up to 50% in
the open space District then to me that
it feels like we're sort of moving out
of an open space District if that makes
any sense so is that is are there only
specific uses that are special except
uses like maybe I don't know if I'm
making any sense here I I can I think I
know where you're going I can try to
help out with that so um it's not
related to any specific use as some
would you know a special exception use
um however the uses that are in the um
po District are very limited
so there's really not a lot of options
other than what we're adding in right
now so Recreation has always been a use
but the recreation wants to expand kind
of their resources that they provide so
that's the reason behind some of those
Recreation amendments but generally I
think it will only be a school
recreation in you know kind of those
General parks and open space
requirements major preserve that kind of
thing perfect that's that's yeah and
Lauren did agree assessment of like the
lots that would be affected by this
zoning Amendment um and if you want she
can probably give you some more detail
on that but there's very very few that
have the acreage um that aren't in the
flood plane that aren't owned by
non-public entities that wouldn't be
like doing adjustments to them or like
mostly right away that type of thing
that that helps a lot concern and yeah
my final question is just interested in
hearing more about what comments the
lcpc had and and how they're addressed
address sure so one of the concerns from
from the lcpc did have to do with kind
of this encroachment idea like are we
going to start losing park space you
know what if schools decide to just
start building kind of in the Parks and
that's what led the city to do an
analysis of the PO districts and so we
we took all of the PO districts and we
kind of divided them up and just to give
you just some like rough numbers um 60
of We There were 101 Parcels 60 of them
are less than one
and so right away you get rid of those
and then another um 14 Parcels were
between 1 and 5 Acres the reason that
that's important is because there's a 5
acre minimum to build an elementary
school okay and so then when you go to
kind of the other end and you look at
the largest 10
Parcels five of those Parcels are owned
either by the county or by the county
parks department one is owned by the
Rockford Foundation one is owned by the
Longs Park Foundation one is a cemetery
and two are owned by the city but
they're located on the Sunnyside
Peninsula so when you look at the
parcels that are actually available to
do something like this you're very
limited and so the the county kind of
because of the County's comments we did
we did go in that direction to make
sure great those are my questions thank
you Lauren just to be clear we're Rec
amending this change to city council to
approve correct
correct I
commission
comments any public
comments I'll make a motion to approve
the text map Amendment for the new Price
Elementary School and will second that
motion we have a
motion on the
floor ready for the
question all in favor let it known by
saying I I I I I I I I I oppose I have
motion
carry four step report to Planning
Commission
I'm G to defer bety
tonight hello I wanted to provide you
with an update of kind of where we're at
regarding not just the zoning ordinance
but also the Salo and um the official
map because those are three of like the
large planning components um that are
called out in the comprehensive plan so
we have um C we're currently working
right now on a map Grant from dcad the
deadlines um March 3rd um to request
some additional funds to support this
endeavor since we're adding not just the
zoning but um the official map
Ando uh to the program I had a draft
timeline for you but I made a bunch of
changes to it at the last minute like
not accounting for some things um but
generally we're estimating about um
trying to get the RFP out for that in
the next I'd say by like mid April um
and then allowing for that so hopefully
getting hiring a consultant about the
same time that the um the map rewards
are announced hopefully we will be in
that um group but we do have funding you
know to start the process um but it
would just be additional um be great if
we could you know have a matching Grant
so that process would start with kind of
um establishing the committee review of
all of our ordinances the variances and
waivers that are typically requested um
um all the planning documents that we
have that would relate to the ordinance
changes and then also discussions with
kind of the hiccups we see as City staff
and where those you know barriers are to
an efficient system as best as we can
under the MPC
um so then we'd start with the official
map hoping that it would be the simplest
process and once that's about to the
point where we're starting to do public
um like the actual public notific
requirements for the MPC the 45 day um
time limit then we'll start on the
zoning ordinance um I anticipate that
being the longest process um looking at
like8 to 10 months but most likely it'll
probably be a year um and then once
that's also at the point where it's
ready for the official like MPC public
notification process we'd start on the
Salo I don't anticipate that one taking
quite as long um but in that update we
look at you know incorporating Vision
zero requirements and complete Street
requirements um clarifying the process
that we're currently doing for Land
Development um subdivision and then just
looking at ways we can maybe streamline
that
process so that's where we're at with
that um I also have been working on a um
2025 action plan for the planning
department so it incorporates not just
um Lauren's role Land Development but
also our um public art and historic
preservation uh our land
bank so that's something that we're
working on um for as the department each
Bureau kind of come up with their own
plan I'm hoping to be able to share that
with you next month so you guys can kind
of see how we're incorporating all of
the comp plan amendments into our plan
for
2025 um and then we're also working on a
spreadsheet that shows all of the action
items that were outlined in the
comprehensive plan
and where um things are already complete
so it's more of a status update you know
if we're in the process of doing stuff
it's in the planning phase that type of
thing so I hope to have those available
all for you at the
next in the next
month so but with the Adu discussion we
were thinking that that would be a great
way for the Planning Commission to start
getting involved in the process so I'm
going to defer to Andrew unless anyone
has questions for me uh if I could just
uh maybe more of a comment uh Betsy than
a question so and this is not meant to
be a critique at all but we're you know
like we're now a year and a half almost
past the approval of the comp plan uh
we're in a housing crisis and you know a
number of our strategies that are listed
in the comp plan around adding
additional housing units like we can't
do because of our zoning code um so it's
a little concerning and I know that
there's been a lot of Staff turnover and
this St again not a critique to you to
Lauren but it's just concerning that you
know we're just now starting this
process and it's going to take another
year um so that's my comment uh the
question is is there like loow hanging
fruit in the zoning code that could be
prioritized and done faster you know
like I think of you know we still have
this ordinance that prohibits more than
like three unrelated people living
together which to me is the definition
of family like can we can we identify
those things that like we all know need
to change uh and that are constricting
our housing Supply and FasTrack
those um I'm we're definitely open to it
I think it depends on you know how much
of that low hanging
fruit is I guess quantity of that low
hanging fruit so whether or not it makes
sense to continuously do zoning ORD
zoning ORD amendments as we go along um
and you know pay the cost of doing the
public notice and that but if it's I
think it really depends on
quantity py is there any way and I'm
kind I'm speaking from my own experience
but if there is any way to utilize
volunteers um from the city Alliance
elts specifically the community and
economic development one I know there
are several members that are eager to to
help you um I know it's come up at our
last couple meetings I'm one of them but
there's there's a bunch of us we really
want to help so if there's anything we
can do just let us know I mean I I
honestly think kind of starting with
like the these kind of hiccups in our
ordinance like if it's the definition of
family or adus that we can call
attention to and kind of get a game plan
for so once we start that rewrite
process it's a simple fix and not
something that needs to you don't need
to go into that research and background
on so I think that would be a good place
to
start So based off of what Mr St said a
moment ago um the housing crisis that
our community is currently in um I've
been curious to know have you sat down
with um some of the developers within
our local community to ask where their
major pain points are um from from a
fast tracking standpoint I'm not so much
interested in the lwh hanging fruit I'm
interested in what can actually drive
this community um in its right direction
and make it affordable for more than
what it is currently available um and I
think um sitting down with some of our
local developers and trying to
understand where they're running into
bumps and hurdles um in order for them
to overcome some of their projects that
can be maybe more towards Middle Market
rather than a higher end um you know um
apartment complex um but something that
something that helps them be able to
produce something that's more cost
efficient for them where they can have
better rates um I know parking
requirements are a big deal I know we
have some mixed use um opportunities
based off what the comprehensive plan is
saying and and limiting or lowering some
of those parking requirements lowering
some of those commercial components to
it um and I just think that it would be
worthwhile to have a conversation to
better understand where they are what
their pain points are and then how we
can continue to move that ball forward
um not so just I'm really excited to see
this Happ as well I think everybody here
is I think we all share that same
sediment we probably all have different
thoughts and feelings on how to move
this ball forward um and I think that um
you know if anybody on this commission
can help you or help connect you with
somebody that can help you I think that
we're all willing to do that thank you
yeah my plan is to talk to both
developers and Engineers who are kind of
dealing with the day-to-day details of
in going through that process so it it
is um on my agenda for next
month so yeah uh I think I'm in
agreement where commissioner stlu said
is that um because I think his point
about lwh hanging fruit is n necessarily
about like it's more about what is the
simplest thing we can do legally that's
not a general comprehensive code update
um in this interim period and to your
point we can do those things like we're
do we're doing one right now right uh
but if we do them one off one off one
off one off one off there is additional
advertising cost and whatnot as well as
just you're assembling a new document
every time um my question is to lwh hang
fruit actually and the comprehensive
plan is is how easy would it be for us
to um for example put more authori on
developing single family housing in all
zones except r
one well I think that kind of gets into
the discussion we're going to have on
adus um because we in all residential
districts we allow more than one
principal use so a moratorium on single
family homes
is I wouldn't want to get into the
legality of it I'd want to check with
the solicitor my understanding is it's
really not something that is
recommended okay but I don't know if any
of the other people in the room have
more experience with that because like
I've thought about this a lot and I
think the area where single family
housing single family DET I should
specify detached not single family
housing single family detached housing
uh adus are where I started going yeah I
wouldn't want to eliminate that option
and already develop Parcels of the city
where doing a single family attached
house not going through a subd
development plan makes sense but at the
same time I don't want to see some of
the undeveloped parts of the city
somewhat
suban um so yeah that's just my general
thoughts I would be interested in
hearing what the solicitor has to say uh
maybe more direct question could we
amend the zoning ordinance temporarily
via attachment to the zoning
code
um I'm not 100% sure what specifically
you're asking about so we're
anticipating doing an overarching zoning
code update in a year with the
comprehensive Plan update I'm wondering
if there's kind of quick and dirty way
of amending the zoning code in the
interum where maybe in more of like
a like an attachment capacity like hey
we are specifying that for example in
all zones single family detached housing
is no longer permitted uh until recced
and we're anticipating an update coming
later so why go through all the details
that of amending every single line of
zoning code if and it's an if it really
is a question I don't know if we could
just buy essentially declaration say we
intend for this to happen it requires a
lot of updates we're expecting a bigger
update later so this stands in place
over the things that we don't have the
time to update am I making sense you are
making sense I've never experienced that
in any situation that I've been in in
the state of Pennsylvania or other
states that I've worked in typically you
have to go Section by section to say I'm
amending this section to read XYZ so
you'd have to amend either the table or
you know um our zoning ordinances
written a little different so typically
like you would have you know what's
allowed on each zoning District so as
more detailed so it could just be a
matter of amending the table okay I
would I would also just add to that you
have to understand kind of the um the
domino effect
of zoning and So within a zoning
ordinance it's inevitably inevitably
going to reference another one yeah and
so as soon as you start making
amendments in a zoning ordinance the
it's it's messy it's messy work so to
just do an overlay is is pretty much
impossible because if one ordinance
refers to something else that's not
getting overlaid you end up with a big
mess
yeah and we have like identified where
some of those issues are but I think one
of the big things that we're struggling
with is inconsistencies between
ordinances and what is going to be the
overall you know deciding factor on
whether or not that issue is getting
resolved so whether it's you know
subdivision and Land Development and
storm water subdivision in Land
Development and Zoning or zoning and
shade tree like all of those have to be
looked at to make sure that we're not
making things worse
um I completely understand where you're
going I just don't think it's as simple
as you know doing a quick text Amendment
like that just for clarification
purposes when you um talked about
everything kind of meddling together um
and you specifi sh commission hisor
commission zoning commission Etc does
that um transfer to the various um like
a mixed use area or R1 or R2 or
or it's more like in the Land
Development process and whether or not
that use is permitted so if that use is
a different use than what's currently
existing then that triggers more
ordinance requirements generally which
would then you know if they're doing a
minor Land Development plan then that
triggers more of the tree requirements
but it really kind of depends on what
it's not like per zoning District like
if we brought into the zoning districts
and you know made just residential and
mixed use and maybe some you know
commercial then you're still going to
have some of those issues because the
zoning is not just the permitted uses
it's other regulations as well which
include landscaping and buffers and
parking and all of that yes thank you
thank you getting my own self confused
there so I appreciate CL I have a
question um out of curiosity does the
city currently like track information
like the the type of housing units that
are being uh built in the city and and
also you know how uh completed a
developments like multif family some of
the apartment complexes that have gone
up recently how they're performing in
terms of you know uh their lease rate
and I asked that because I think it
would be really helpful to really have a
strong database of you know what housing
has been is being built in the city and
also how well does that match up to the
kind of housing that you know that we
need I've seen some really great great
studies I think might been one from East
later that um really was showing
basically here's what the market is
producing in terms of Housing and then
here's what you know here's the size of
households in our community there's
almost always a huge mismatch granted
those are for more you know Spa
townships not necessarily a city like
Lancaster um because I think that that's
important to whatever housing changes
housing related changes we make to the
zone ordinance you know I absolutely
agree there are definitely some low
fruit changes like
adus removing the capital number of
unrated people that can live in a house
you very simple straightforward things
but we certainly want to make sure we
don't make any changes that turns out
that's not what the market is building
and also that's not what our residents
need in terms of the housing types you
know uh uh so I was just curious you
know if there if that's any thought
processing going on or that's something
that the city's already been doing so we
have the interim housing strategy which
kind of looks at those um comparisons so
we've been using that we do track
residential units but not
necessarily currently we're not
measuring those what type of unit what
housing unit it is um that is something
that I'm working on with codes to try to
get a better understanding of our system
is a little clunky a lot clunky um to be
able to like run reports and stuff
there's like one person that is really
good at it so I'm on her list of people
to work with but yeah that would be the
ideal is to have the different types of
housing that's built and then as far as
like success of those um I think we
would probably work most with like LC to
kind of get an understanding of that
software is off in the ailles hill of
any any planing Department well and
that's part of the problem you know
we're in the process of updating our
software we're switching from Unice to
City View um that's also taking time so
we hope to be able to do a lot more um
data collection and metrics once that's
in place not just um number of housing
units but also like length of time
things are taking to go through the
process because I think that's a really
important factor to look at and to see
if these amendments um you know make a
difference in that excellent thank you
any other
questions I would just add if you have
these little hanging fruit please text
me like we have a list running of things
that we know are issues so just send me
an email with the information that
you're aware of um I'm happy to kind of
add it to a list and if there's this
short-term text amendment that we can
feasibly do that's not going to be like
a huge impact um then I I think we would
definitely look at doing
that all right thank you thank
you up business a accessory dwelling
units adus
if you give me just a second I'm just
bringing up
my my little note section so I can see
it
better I appreciate that thanks okay
great that's perfect all right well my
name is Andrew wh and I have served now
on the Planning Commission for the last
four years and one of the things that I
would like to give introduction to with
this discussion is
that one of my goals with signing up for
this was to work with like-minded people
like all of us here and probably in the
audience as well to find ways that we
could really work to provide housing of
all kinds for people in the city and one
of the ways that I believe we can kind
of reach that common goals through
except three dwelling units and I think
a great solution to our housing problem
and one of the things I believe we do a
lot of times is we react as a Planning
Commission someone comes in with an idea
and we react to those demands and we are
here is maybe less planning more
reactionary and I believe that today by
maybe setting up these steps for
something cohesive with adus we can
maybe get ahead of it a little
bit for our audience and maybe even
members of the commission who are
wondering what are exactly adus
accessory dwelling units um really the
definition which I think kind of brings
a couple of the ideas together is it's
an independent self-sufficient dwelling
unit with a complete kitchen and bath
facilities adus can be converted
portions of an existing home which is
called an internal Adu it could be an
addition to a new or existing home which
would be called an attached Adu or it
could be a standalone accessory
structure or converted portions of an
existing Standalone accessory structure
which would be called a detached adus
essentially
we're thinking preferred ideas would be
like an apartment or if you've heard of
the granny flat before where another
member of the family like can live there
and they can be on that same property
and share a lot of the things but they
still have their own bathroom they still
have their own kitchen they still have
their own means to get out of that house
without having to cut through your
living room um these are not meant to be
bed and breakfast they're not meant to
be boarding houses that's a completely
separate definition but I know this
might stir up things a little bit it
could possibly become a short-term
rental some places have done that I'm
not trying to stir the bucket on that
I'm just saying that's one of the
definitions that some places have used
for
it um just visual examples of maybe what
an Adu can look like in an urban
environment we even have these already
in the city believe it or not they might
just be going by different names you
have the basement or the interior Adu
walk down the stairs there it is
separate entrance you have a complete
living situation um one of my personal
favorites is the carriage house or the
detached Adu which goes over a garage
for me that's the low hanging fruit in
Lancaster I think that's something we
can see a lot of movement done in a very
succinct way and then there's also um
Studio attic or again another kind of
interior Adu um I'm not sure if the
picture I showed with that is exactly by
definition what it is but the idea that
again you have a separate entrance a
separate way you can get out to the
street without cutting through the rest
of the home to get
there um we've already talked about this
in 2023 when we did our comprehensive um
plan um our future Lancaster it
specifically envisioned the idea of an
Adu and it calls on us to create a clear
approval pathway for property owners
looking to add an accessory B unit and
essentially we're supposed to use our
powers to help reduce the Reg barriers
to get to that it's right in our plans
that we spent lots of time thinking
through Consulting with others so we we
have the kind of initiative to do
that um another strategy on the next
slide would come from the 2015 lster
city um Alliance plan building on
strength same idea they suggested a
development Clearing House which would
establish a One-Stop shop to facilitate
really less experienced developers and
businesses
and make it possible for people who
don't have legal teams who don't have
engineering teams but who have maybe
that desire to work towards this goal of
providing housing to just provide the
resources that we as a city can do and
through other means to make it happen
and really help bridge some of the
gaps and then of course um thank you by
the way for bringing this um to our
conversation here's our current um
ordinance I guess would be the best way
to describe it right and this is
probably a good launching point for what
it would actually
um involved for today's discussion for
tonight's discussion kind of what the
actual ordinance looks like that we have
right now in the books um maybe a place
that we can launch from there I want to
come back to the slide in a minute
because I know we'll probably actually
want to stare at it and kind of really
look at the bo but I have one last slide
before we get get to
that um I wanted to just also throw out
some brainstorming ideas for the
commission or even the public for that
much we always love public input on this
but um brainstorming ideas for actually
implementing it um things that have
worked in other places things that I
know would work here providing
one-on-one technical assistance to
applicants who want Do It um hosting
periodic workshops or educational
sessions for potential
applicants um one of my personal
favorite ideas is creating a catalog of
pre-approved building plans for adus
what happened after World War II
seriously there's like a serious catalog
of buildings that you can choose from
and you can build and I think we can do
this as a city we can find some common
plans that would work we can reduce City
fees as well we could bundle some of
these ideas together and make it very
palatable for people to jump in and say
hey I can do this in my
backyard um and finally we could make a
decision to either maybe per permit all
internal attached and detach adus by
right or maybe we could permit all
internal attach or detach adus by right
in some of the districts and then make
it a discretionary use in other
districts so we have a lot of ideas here
I know I just said all that in I think
it was under 3 minutes that was my goal
in case I had to do public comment and
that was lightning fast but thank
goodness they're on slides we can go
back to them if we need to but I hope
that gets the ball ring I don't want to
hear my voice anymore it Echo I we have
such a full commission here but I hope
that helped get the ball rolling a
little bit thank you for allowing me to
start the conversation I really
appreciate you putting the presentation
together Andrew thank you um actually I
like I'll get on I'll put some momentum
in this rolling ball I guess um because
I think you're right we we especially
need the help with facilitation of those
sort of projects um and I know something
that not a lot of people
realize is so let's say you wanted to
put an accessory dwelling unit over your
garage so fire code starts to become a
big thing then because the the code you
can't you need you potentially need
sprinklers I believe I think it'd be
interesting we as a commission could get
um a codes official in here sometime and
have kind of an open discussion about
certain scenarios it might help us when
we're working on zoning revisions
because we'll know what certain building
types are possible based off certain
constraints like code
um and I'm just going to throw it out
there I Me Maybe it helps us as a city
determine maybe we need to make some
amendments to those more concerning
codes like fire building code we do have
the ability to amend those things it's
just uh you have to be more intentional
because it could open you up to
liability so I have a question um just
kind of what Mr Dasher was just saying
made me think about this um if you guys
recall when we talked about the
short-term rentals um and there were
some safety concerns regarding
short-term rentals and how they are uh
managed and monitored essentially uh
regulated um there are so in the case
that a short-term an accessory dwelling
unit would be used as a short-term
rental not a
long-term situation um I think that they
should be held to higher safety
standards particularly if it is above a
grad unit um I think there should be
considerations or thoughts about how we
can ensure that
that unit is safer for from a short-term
rental standpoint
because my thought is and I have no
valid validity to this is that in in
some cases I would think that you're
some people aren't going to care about
that space from a short-term rental
renting situation as you would in a home
that you're going to live in for a a
long period of time whether that is
you're purchasing that home or you're
renting that home from somebody else
you're going to care for that particular
property differently than you would if
it was a short-term rental so I just say
that because I think it should be
thought of from a safety Factor as we
continue this conversation I'm really
excited about it I think um accessory
dwelling units can offer a lot
particularly when it comes to a variety
of rent options and affordability um I
also think can help certain homeowners
um maintain their home um and make that
a little bit more affordable as well and
lessen the burden of you know um just
lessen the burden of things so I safety
is a concern and I don't know what the
right answer is but it's where my
thoughts
went yeah just think back on that I do I
like the idea of thinking about
short-term rentals I mean I agree with
the safety points but I think one of the
challenges with adus is just they're
expensive I mean you know everything is
expensive to build so has a way of
incentivizing more adus if there was a
way to allow them to be short-term
rentals um you know makes it a little
bit more feasible I think for the
property owner um I'm also curious um I
don't know if this question is for bets
or Lauren uh I I would be interested in
looking at sort of all of the
regulations around adus you know so
there's like lot coverage there's
setback um I still am like curious about
the alley access requirement and if
that's something that most other cities
are doing uh so I think right now you
have to have public alley access you get
a variance for common alleys that really
limits the number of places where you
could do adus in the city because a lot
of bar Parcels don't have alley access
so I understand again from a safety
perspective but is Aly access like a
real requirement or is the are there
other variations or is there something
that's less rigent that still allows it
to be uh safe so those are some of my
questions am is one of the things I was
thinking about when when these ideas
were kind of being put into a a slot
was
that take rock or ice or some of the
streets at least in the Northeast area
where I live and how it's an entire
block of just garages something like
that would be an easier one for me to
visualize and to be able to say let's
put this on a map this is an area we can
make plans for versus some of the other
places with the shared alleys or really
impossible backyards to get to where
yeah not in my backyard it shouldn't
happen there um it would make more sense
for other places um yeah you're right
there's a lot to think about with that I
will say that um bety and I have
reviewed um what's called the model
ordinance and uh we have one for the
local level which we thought would be
helpful to share after this conversation
we didn't want to give you all of that
and then also you know bring all of that
into the conversation but it is uh it's
very interesting to see kind of what the
model ordinance would include and kind
of use that to figure out what would fit
in Lancaster there are some kind of
research examples I think Andrew you
might have alluded to that during your
presentation you just have to really be
careful that they fit um and so
sometimes you know the the cities that
have the research are also cities that
are
um maybe a little bit ahead of the city
of Lancaster in terms of their
open-mindedness to Alternative housing
so um you know the the the research is
limited and the research that is out
there is sometimes slanted um toward
cities that don't have a lot in common
with Lancaster and so that being the
case there are often takeaways like
there might be um an appendix that shows
some like really worthwhile information
to a report and so you say okay well the
report doesn't really You Know cover
what we need but this appendix is great
to have as a resource and so um I would
always encourage you to look for those
things I also um have been doing some of
that and like I said um I I did assume
that after this meeting when I send out
the minutes I'm going to also send along
that model ordinance for your
consideration
great then Lauren just a maybe a quick
question so right now if you wanted to
build an edu how does the utility hookup
work is it a separate utility hookup or
are you going off of the other
building you're going off of the other
building okay okay so that was probably
my biggest my biggest question was just
getting Public Water and Sewer to these
adus um and the challenges around that I
Andrew I think it's a great idea and I I
love the idea of having some conceptual
architectural plans that could maybe
help some people um I think the reality
is that you're going to get a different
Co you're going to get a different
building every time that you do it and
it's all going to each one of them is
going to have their own code challenges
that you'll have to meet so it can't
really be a I don't see it personally
ever being a pre-approved building floor
plan but I do think it could be helpful
um to show you know minimal space
requirements for kitchens things like
that and and kind of fit them to the
space that you have I think that would
help certainly especially for someone
who doesn't have the resources to hire
an architect or um an engineer or
something like that in order to do it um
but remind people what 400 square fet
looks like right yeah it's it's it's
very tiny but yeah you know and we kind
of talked about this Betsy at the city
Alliance meeting but I think the public
utility thing is probably the the
biggest question I have is if I have a
building in the back of my house which I
don't but if I did and I wanted to build
um you know or I wanted to have somebody
live there can I connect to the sewer
line and what would be the process in
order to do that sewer and
water yeah I just wanted to add on the
model ordinance it is a um it was
prepared by ARP um but it is being
sponsored throughout the state um by the
PA Housing Coalition um and the
Pennsylvania American Planning
Association so that's where we got the
reference to it um but it is something
obviously is a Statewide issue and it's
one way to encourage doing this I think
an assessment of like what Lots might
work if there's lots that have existing
you know the mapping component I think
would also be really important because
we can highlight which properties that
would even work for if you're doing a
detached one um I think where our
current
ordinance kind of conflicts with stuff
as if you are allowing both a detached
unit and a or unit so say it's in your
basement or whatever and are you then
you know is that a residence is that
turning into a duplex or how do you
distinguish between the two because
that's not really another principal use
um so I think that's one of the things
that needs to be
considered I was going to ask kind of
similar to what you alluded to there an
indoor unit essentially you're turning
it into a
multi-unit right like an indoor
accessory dwelling unit you're saying
you're taking a single family home and
turning into a two
unit right and I think it depends on the
size and that I think that's where like
the nuances in zoning are what really
need to be looked at but um to your
point you know it's not just utilities
and the street I think storm water is
also one of the issues if you're doing
one and I Lauren um I don't if you want
to share kind of the feedback you got on
that
I don't suppose is it Tom is it Tom is
here and so he is the one that actually
sent the email and triggered this
conversation so I don't know if you want
to just bring him up now versus waiting
for like public comment
or I'll defer to
you I can come on up Tom just make sure
you give us your name and your address
please for the record
uh sure thing um my name is Tom Riner
and um I live at 335 Ruby Street in the
southwest part of the city and um I saw
the announcement in the agenda that this
would be discussed today and I was very
interested in this because we are
currently in the process of building an
Adu um our lot is kind of unique because
it's a little bit bigger compared to the
other Lots on the side it's a detached
uh Four Square from
1923 and and there's an existing Garage
on site that we demolished we went
through the zoning approval we went
through historic approval and uh
we're trying to submit to uh storm water
and um and U building code for
approval and um I mean I'm I'm
interested in taking what I've learned
and kind of helping other people to do
this because I think the adus are a
really great thing to have we're doing a
it's a one-bedroom dwelling unit above a
two-car
garage and so the total square footprint
is 690 I think I had said 790 in my
email which was incorrect but then once
you include the EES and everything we
have about a one foot Eve then you're
looking at about 800 square feet for the
Adu um it's not massive but what you end
up is you run into storm water issues
and my email I was saying that you know
I I understand the importance of not
dumping our sewage into the Koga River
and I totally agree with that um but on
the ground it's a very hard thing to
work with and the stormw water team uh
Angela and Kate are very good to work
with I have no complaints um but
the difficulty of keeping an Adu project
under a th square
feet is um is significant because in our
case you're looking at 800 sare ft for
just the roof and then by the time we
added on sidewalk and then a little
patio
area and to my surprise I figured out
that or I I I understood that like even
a staircase like a wood stair coming up
even if it's not attached to the ground
is still considered
impervious um I'm not sure why because I
figured that the water would just go
through it and into the ground but but
then we found ourselves you know
slightly above 1,000 square fet and
we're looking at it trying to nip and
Tuck and trying to keep it under th000
square feet but then at a certain point
we figured you know we just we just got
to do it we just got to gota swallow the
pill and and do it and by the time you
get into a large storm water plan then
um you're looking at dealing with a
civil engineer to do a stormw water
management
plan um you have to have a surveyor come
to survey the property to do the
Topography of the of the property and
then you have to have a um a GE
geotechnical engineer come and then
they'll dig Pits on the site and then
test the percolation of the
site so we've gone through all of that
we've developed a plan and um I mean the
soft costs associated with that are
probably going to be around like
177,000 and then the cost of actually
doing the infiltration bed that we're
looking at um I don't know probably
going to be about 10 15,000 I'm not
exactly sure
so what I would
suggest is that if you're looking at any
Adu project um you have to consider how
it's going to interface with um some of
these other
requirements and um you know I thought a
lot about it um I don't know what
allowance there is what a possibility
there is to bump up the threshold from a
thousand square feet to you know like
say 1,400 Square ft 1500 square ft I
don't know if there's an allowance
for being able to take some credit for
existing impervious on site in our case
we're actually reducing the total number
of impervious area on site but we still
have to do the storm water solution
because um you know the goal is to get
rid of all you know impervious in the
city of Lancaster or to have some sort
of management process in place for all
of these all these locations so
um I I really like the idea of doing the
adus especially above the garages but
you have to understand that for the
garages you know I I'm actually also a
structural engineer so I know that in
order to put a dwelling unit on top of a
garage you probably have to um rip down
this the cinder blocks that are there
and then dig a substantial Foundation
then by the time you're doing that then
you're getting into
you know pretty significant project and
um if there's any ability to kind of
massage some of the the requirements to
make this one thing a little bit easier
I think that'd be something to really
think
about to you do you have a sense of how
much like total cost this is going to be
for you if you are able to get this
thing built um yeah yeah I mean we're
going to be able to do it so it's just
uh you know more expensive than we
thought it would be could you give me
like a ball r or ballpark figure of how
much like total cost you'll be in um I
mean for the for the garage and the Adu
I think the latest number is like
130 how how many so what was your total
square footage like how how many how how
large um the footprint of the Adu is 690
okay but it so it's a thous it's over a
th000 square fet that triggers the large
storm water yes it's
sorry yes that's so yeah sorry how many
square feet are
you um well the it's it's a thousand
square feet of new
impervious and then I think uh 3,000 of
disturbed Earth
I so even like a patio or a sidewalk
that runs next to the house next to the
Adu all of that is considered new
impervious it's it's 5,000 Earth
disturbance 5,000 okay thank you
and, square feet of impervious or
existing impervious since disturb right
right yeah so it's really like the the
footprint plus the eaves that you have
to consider then plus whatever sidewalks
or patios we had all goes into the same
bucket
uh question for you because you are
building one with a garage what fire
code requirements do do you have to
abide by for the garage you do need
sprinkers right no no not under the
current building code okay um there's a
1 hour separation that's required one
hour separation so 5/8 inch typex gypsum
okay so between the garage between yeah
that's between the garage and the
dwelling unit up above you didn't have a
garage wouldn't it would just be normal
structure correct
yeah I appreciate you uh sending an
email and being a little open with us
about the process you're going through
because unfortunately part of the only
way we're going to make this more
affordable for other residents is to
know the pains and the experience of
people like yourself um I hope that when
your project reaches completion you're
open to sharing like documents with uh
Us and other residents because maybe we
can use that as a model I agree with
commissioner hack that like you know
we're definitely going to uh see sites
with unique conditions that it's hard to
just cookie cutter things but at the
same time we have a lot of the same size
Parcels in the city and I do think that
something like Mr uh commissioner whal
is proposing having like a packet for
people could be viable for a sizable
portion um so just just thank you for
being with us and I hope it continues
yeah sure thing thank you just out of
curiosity um is this Abu for will you
rent this for additional income your
property will you keep this for family
or what are your I'm just curious out of
what are your intentions um I mean our
intentions are to rent it yeah um in a
long-term situation and then if the need
arises to make it available for family
okay thank you sure
than I also just want to add um this was
a very timely conversation because in my
work I recently came across um The Alley
house project in Bethlehem uh which is a
really interesting project if you have
the opportunity to read about you know
Aly an alley house it's a historic form
of adus you can see them around
Lancaster as well just all the little
twostory row houses that are on alleys
all over the city at least where they
haven't been all demolished for parking
um and they actually did I think a lot
of the things that we've been talking
about today where they took a um I don't
recall if they hired a consult to do
this or not but they took a you know a
full review of the city identified all
the places where it was possible to
build alley houses
um propos changes to their zoning
ordinance and I think right now where
they are is they are identifying
specific homeowners who are willing to
engage with the project and there might
be some sort of fundraising partnership
where they actually assist the
homeowners to actually construct Adu so
a lot of parts are outside of the zoning
coordinance but I think it's a really
interesting model and I can provide a
link to it um for folks or just look up
the AL house project in Bethlehem I
think it makes for a very interesting
read um also points you know and again
this is outside of the Planning
Commission and the zoning that there
just might have to be some new
Partnerships involved fundraising
involved to to make at least the
beginning in Con in conjunction with a
lot of the ordinance changes we're we're
proposing you know to make constructing
adus uh for homeowners more a more
affordable Prospect so partnering
partnering with a lot of the same folks
who are already engaged in the
affordable housing scene you know how
can we work together with them to you
know if we do find homeowners who are
interested in in getting involved in
this project especially if you know they
may be of a you know lower income
homeowners folks were on a fixed income
were needing sort of that extra income
stream to be able to stay in their homes
um that's be potential opportunity to to
get involved but um anyway I thought
that was just a just within the last
couple days I looked that up so thank
you Porter I just pulled it up on my
phone yeah and it I mean the alleys look
very similar to what in lancas so I
think that that would be a great
resource so I appreciate your you're
bringing that to our attention yeah it's
it's hard to sometimes find examples
that aren't like Portland working EXA it
was really nice to find something that
was in Central PA yeah no that's great
thank you yeah I just want to add to
that I was at a conference a couple
months ago where they presented about
that I think in some cases they're using
manufactured housing to lower some of
the housing cost but yeah I think that's
a good model to look at uh and then just
to again you back on Porter like what I
often see in my work is we have a lot of
you know we have large homes and we have
a lot of sing like single people on a
fixed income living in a four or five
bedroom house that in some cases they
own out right but you know they're older
it's hard to maintain those homes it's
hard for them to age in place because of
the stairs in a lot of cases they have
large Parcels that would work for an Adu
and if we could figure out how to get
that you buil you know move that person
into the Adu which is a much more you
know suitable uh house for them allows
them to stay in the neighborhood agent
place and then get rental income from
the house while also maximizing you know
the bedrooms that you're using in that
house the family ideally would move in
like we need to figure out how to do
that kind of stuff because the
opportunity is definitely there um so
that's my Shel um I am curious Lauren do
you know how many adus do we have
lanaster
no we are hoping to potentially get an
intern this
summer so I mean you know you to build
an ad you have to go through the Land
Development process right so we do we
just not track
it so it doesn't necessarily go through
the Land Development process and so it
it does generally goes through zoning
and so um we do there have been like a
couple of tiny houses that have been
built and those are in Land Development
the other issue we have and you know in
full transparency is again the software
that we use does not make it easy to
track things from Department to
department so I could be tracking
something in Land Development and it's
being tracked in zoning or even in codes
and to find to connect all those things
even on a single
property becomes really messy and
so um we're hoping without putting too
much faith in a software program that
our new software can be able to provide
us the ability to create some of those
reports and track things more
efficiently makes sense thank
you yeah I I just also wanted to add
some things to say I think that as part
of the conversation about use Asti to
short-term rentals we need to be mindful
that um you know the use can impact the
return on investment for people uh
that's a factor in in these
conversations I think another factor in
the conversation is the complexity of
the resulting zoning changes overall
that we produce um you know I'm I'm not
a huge fan of the way we do use based
zoning I'm more of a form-based zoning
fan myself um
that being said I have some
philosophical conceptions but
um if we create a zoning code that's
easy to follow with not a lot of
complexity I think that will help
encourage development in the city not
only great to use but other forms of
development as well because the more
complex your code is the more time and
money you have to spend in staff time
which is another component of cost when
it comes to these projects so um yeah
those those are just my final thoughts
on need to
use I think this has been a really good
productive start it's just good kickoff
so I appreciate this being brought to
our
attention thank you
Andrew yeah thank you Andrew excellent
idea um I think the adus
U I don't know if you Envision them to
be U families or single units mostly
single units
perhaps that's what I'm thinking
especially based on the fact that um the
cost is high for a larger unit but um
bottom line we do need housing
affordable housing in the
city and uh hopefully we can move
forward with this and begin to um not
make things uh as complicated as they
are
now uh as you mentioned commissioner
Dashner so um good comment any other
public
comment
yes hi oops hi good oops sorry good
evening my name is Phil St Kennedy I am
a member of member of the traffic
commission I live at on the unit block
of Chester Street in southeast
and I'm just encouraged to hear you all
uh talk so much about the affordable
housing crisis and about um some ways
that we can be aggressive in in
confronting that I'm really supportive
of adus I would like to see you know
minimum number of requirements possible
to make it as streamlined and as as easy
for folks as possible I love the
suggestion of
um preset designs while they might not
work in all circumstances you know there
are a lot of cases where people are
going to win a build over garages so
like having something ready to go that
someone can just grab off the shelf I
think would make it a lot easier um I I
also want to say in regards to like the
alley access I know that we have a lot
of blocks like mine where we don't have
an alley uh but we do have space in
between the houses so they're basically
duplexes even though they're kind of
elro homes where there is Street access
and so I would encourage you to be open
to situations like that um so that you
don't eliminate a lot of potential you
know potential housing in the city um
and related to the zoning rewrite as
well I just um encourage you to be as
aggressive as you can in finding ways to
allow more allow more housing so thank
you thank you thank
you any other public
comment see we have distinguished Miss
Paul Jackson here
did you want to say
anything very very interested in the
process and I'll be talking to
your
okay good to see
you so do I have a motion to a
Jour I'll make a motion to adjourn I'll
second motion to adjourn and a second
all in FA let know by saying I I
I
I have it meeting the
Jour at 657
657 thank you